Hi. This is Matt Baker. Today I’m going to
show you a chart from 1858 that displays
some statistics about the signers of the
US Declaration of Independence. Every now
and then I like to take a look at vintage
pre-computer age charts like this because:
A. I find them to be quite aesthetically
pleasing; and B. They can give us some
interesting insight into how people thought
about the past in the past. So, first of all,
here’s what the Declaration of Independence
looks like. As you can see at the bottom,
it was signed by 56 individuals, with the most
prominent signature be that of John Hancock, who,
at the time, was the President
of the Continental Congress.
So, what this chart does is it takes those
56 signatures and places them one per row,
starting with John Hancock. After Hancock,
the names are arranged by state (shown here),
roughly going from north to south. So, we can
see that Pennsylvania had the most signers (9)
and Rhode Island had the least (with only 2) but
that all 13 colonies were represented. However,
what the chart does not show is that there were
actually 6 additional British colonies nearby that
did not sign. These were, to the north: Quebec,
Nova Scotia, St. John’s Island, and Newfoundland
(all of which are now a part of Canada) and
to the south: East Florida and West Florida
(which were first of all, ceded back to Spain but
then eventually did become part of the US later).
Now, next to the name of each signer, we
also get their date of birth, place of birth,
education, and profession. I’ll come to back
to the birthdates in a moment but for now,
take note that, of the 56 signers, only 48 were
born in the colonies. The others included 3 born
in Ireland, 2 in Scotland, 2 in England,
and 1 in Wales. As for their educations,
31 are marked as having either a collegiate,
academic, or classical education (which,
I presume, means that they received some sort
of a higher degree). 12 are marked as having a
“liberal” education (which, a note at the bottom
explains as meaning that their education was good
but that they didn’t actually graduate from any
particular institution). Finally, 9 are marked
as having finished a common schooling only, and
4 are listed as being either home-schooled or
self-taught. When it comes to their professions,
the most common, by far, was lawyer, followed by
merchant. But there were also 4 physicians,
2 clergyman, and a handful of farmers.
Now, it is at this point in the chart, that
things gets interesting, at least from a design
point of view—because we suddenly get a bunch
of lines going either up or down. Basically,
what is happening is that the signers are getting
re-arranged by their birthdates, or age at the
time of signing, with the oldest now being placed
at the top and the youngest at the bottom. So, for
example, although John Hancock is initially listed
at the top, once things are re-arranged by age,
he ends up way down here at position 39 (meaning
that there were 38 signers who were older than
him). This means that, by using the column marked
III, we can quickly determine who the oldest
signers were as well as the youngest. So, let’s
try it out. This dot here represents the oldest
person to sign the declaration. If we follow
the line to the left we can find out who that
was. If you know your US history, you probably
already guessed that it was Benjamin Franklin
(who was aged 70 at the time). What about the
next oldest though? Well, let’s go back up here
and follow the line. The 2nd oldest was Stephen
Hopkins, at age 69. He was in poor health, which
is why his signature appears very shaky. Let’s now
figure out who the youngest person was. Basically,
we just start with this dot here and follow
it left. And we end up with Edward Rutledge,
who was just 26 years old. The second youngest was
Thomas Lynch Jr., also aged 26. His father, Thomas
Lynch Sr., was supposed to sign but became sick,
so his son—Thomas Jr.—had to fill in for him.
Let’s now go back up to the top of the chart
and take a look at the next two columns.
Column IV indicates how many times the signer
was married. So, one dot (like for Benjamin
Franklin) means once; whereas two dots (like for
Stephen Hopkins) means twice. And if we look down
the list, we can see that no one was married more
than twice. However, there are two rows here with
no dots at all, which means that there were two
signers who never married. Let’s figure out who
those were. Again, we follow the lines to the left
and we end up with Caesar Rodney and Joseph Hewes.
In Hewe’s case, he was engaged but his fiancee
died suddenly just a few days before the wedding.
Now, being that Column IV represents marriages,
you can probably guess what Column V represents.
It represents how many children each signer
had. So, the person with the most dots,
had the most kids. Again, let’s look down the
list and see if anyone stands out. There are
a few with lots of dots but none with more
than this guy here who has 18. Once again,
if we follow the line to the left, we can
find out who it is and in this case it’s
Carter Braxton. He and Benjamin Harrison
(who also signed) were both grandsons
of Robert “King” Carter and thus members
of the famous Carter family of Virginia.
Okay, moving back up to the top we get another
section of criss-crossed lines. Because,
now the chart is going to show the order in
which the signers died. So, this dot here (in
Column VI) represents the first person to
pass away. Following the line to the left,
we first learn that this person had eight
children and only married once. And if we
keep going we find out that the person was
John Morton. In fact he died less than 9
months after the signing of the Declaration
of Independence, probably from tuberculosis.
Let’s now go back up and trace the second
line to find out who the next person was
to pass away. That person was… doot do do do do…
Button Gwinnett, who died just one month later.
Gwinnett is notable for two reasons. First of
all, his name appears on the declaration first,
if we start at the top left. Second, he’s
the only one of the signers to die by duel.
While the Burr–Hamilton duel is more well
know, Hamilton was not one of the signers.
Now, what about the last person to die?
Well, let’s go to the bottom and follow
this line here. It leads to Charles Carroll
of Carrollton, who died in 1832 and who was
the only Catholic to sign the declaration. His
signature is interesting because it’s the only
one that includes a place of residence as
a part of the name. He did this in order
to distinguish himself from his father, who was
known as Charles Carroll of Annapolis. Anyhow,
Charles Carroll of Carrollton is also notable for
one other reason but I’m going to skip that for
now in order to point out the 2nd and 3rd last
persons to die because they happen to be the two
most important individuals on the entire chart
and curiously, they died on the exact same day,
which happened to be July the 4th, exactly 50
years after the signing of the declaration.
If we zoom out and trace those two lines,
we get… John Adams and Thomas Jefferson:
the only two signers who ended up serving as
Presidents (the 2nd and 3rd, respectively).
Take note that George Washington (the 1st
President) was not one of the signers, nor
was James Madison (the 4th President), although
they both later signed the U.S. constitution.
Okay, let me now tell you about the last four
columns. Columns VII and VIII indicate whether
or not the signer left behind a wife or any
children. And the final two columns indicate the
age to which the signer lived. And this is where
we circle back to Charles Carroll of Carrollton
because, not only was he the last signer to
die, he was also the one who lived the longest,
making it to age 95. As for the one who lived
the shortest life, well, let’s take a look.
We have to start at this dot here and then
trace the line all the way up here (because he
was the 4th to die) and then way back down here,
because he was the second youngest to sign. And,
oh, we’ve already talked about him. That was
Thomas Lynch Jr. (the one who signed because
his father got sick). Well, just four years
later, he set sail for the West Indies but
the ship he set sail on… disappeared. So he was
declared, at age 30, to have been “lost at sea”.
Now, if you like charts and you’re interested in
US history, you’ll definitely want to check out
our new Timeline of US History, which is available
as a poster from our website UsefulCharts.com.
It shows how and when each state was formed
as well as providing lots of other important
information such which party held the house,
senate, and presidency at any given time. We
also have a Timeline of World History, a Timeline
of European History as well as lots of historical
family trees so once again, if you’re interested
in learning more about any of these posters,
just head over to UsefulCharts.com or simply click
the link in the description or pinned comment.
Finally, take note that from now until
August 31st, we’ve got a project running
over on Kickstarter, which is an expanded
look at the evolutionary tree of life via
four brand new classification charts.
So, if that sounds interesting to you,
be sure to check that out too. Again, the link
will be in the description and pinned comment.
Thanks for watching.